<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of Charles Trinder, recorder of Gloucester at his entrance upon that office, January the 8th, 1687/8.</title>
            <author>Trinder, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17151202</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17151202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1160:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of Charles Trinder, recorder of Gloucester at his entrance upon that office, January the 8th, 1687/8.</title>
                  <author>Trinder, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687/8 [i.e. 1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"White-Hall, January 21st, 1687/8."</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 16.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:105927:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>White-Hall, January</hi> 21ſt, 1687/8.</p>
            <p>This may be Printed, <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDERLAND,</hi> P.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPEECH OF Charles Trinder, Eſq; RECORDER OF GLOUCESTER, AT HIS <hi>Entrance upon that Office, <hi>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY</hi>
               </hi> the 8th, 1687/8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1687/8.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:105927:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105927:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF Charles Trinder, Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT has pleaſed His Sacred Majeſty to ſend His Royal Mandate hither; in obedience to which, I have had the Honour to be Elected, Admitted, and Sworn Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder of this City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> I am very ſenſible of thoſe many Defects, which may ſeem to others as well as to my ſelf, to render me unqualified for ſo weighty an Office. But I ſhall not here looſe time, either in extenuating or excuſing the ſame. None here are ignorant of thoſe many invincible Obſtacles, as to all ſorts of Learning and Knowledge, which have been laid in the way, to Perſons of my Character and Religion: To mention no more then the very Oaths which we could not take, and for the not taking of which, (till of late) there was no Diſpenſation to be had: Theſe, I ſay, alone, were a too ſufficient cauſe of diſcouragement, and hindrance, from any cloſe purſuit of Study, or Converſation, in ſuch Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Practice, as are requiſit to an accompliſh'd Lawyer.</p>
            <p>But our Comfort is, that in the preſent ſtate of Affairs, not ſo much profoundneſs of Skill, as ſincerity of Heart, not the great Underſtanding, but the good Will, are the moſt indiſpenſable Neceſſaries for His Majeſty's Service; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this, but in moſt other Stations and Employments.</p>
            <p>And for theſe, I may without vanity challenge them to my ſelf; and I hope, being no Stranger to moſt of you here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105927:3"/>preſent, you will eaſily believe and acknowledge the ſame; and that, if on the one ſide, you regard His Majeſty's Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and on the other ſide the circumſtances of my Life and Profeſſion, it would have been, perhaps, difficult to have found any One in this County, more entirely at His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Service then my ſelf.</p>
            <p>And let this ſuffice to juſtifie His Majeſty's Choice, and (notwithſtanding my own avowed Defectiveneſs and Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in other reſpects) my ſubmiſſion to it.</p>
            <p>Mean while, I am not to be put in mind, that even theſe beloved Oualities, which I ſeem to glory in, of Zeal and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in His Majeſty's Service, and which I plead as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for my other Unworthineſſes, that even theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I ſay, are enough to blaſt me in the Opinion of ſome men, who will never hope for any good, from One ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed and declared. The diſtractions and differences of Opinions, have cauſed ſuch diſaffections of Heart, that Mens Fancies are fill'd with Fears and Jealouſies, againſt the moſt innocent and laudable Purpoſes and Proteſtations of this nature, even before they are reduced into Act.</p>
            <p>Hence it comes to paſs, that a Man can no ſooner make profeſſion of his Duty and Zeal to His Majeſty's Service, but ſome diſcontented and ill-affected Worldling, who knows little, and loves leſs (beſides what concerns his own ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt) repreſents him to himſelf and others, as one of the Court-Party, no Friend to his Country, One ready to ſacrifice his own, and all other Mens Liberties and Properties, to the Arbitrary Will and Pleaſure of the Prince.</p>
            <p>Neither does this happen in matters which relate to the Service of the King only, or upon Temporal accounts alone; but alſo, in all Endeavours and good Deſires for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our fellow-Subjects too; and that in things which are Spiritual, and concern the Conſcience only.</p>
            <p>Hence it comes to paſs, that a man cannot compaſſionate the heavy Sufferings of his innocent Neighbours, for matters of meer Religion, but he is preſently maligned by ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got or other, as an Enemy and Underminer of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as I my ſelf was in this very place, for this only cauſe, in the late heats at the Quarter-Seſſions for this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, publickly traduced and branded, as One that did more miſchief then any other Man in the County.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105927:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But let ſuch Worldlings and Bigots give me leave to tell them, <hi>That they know not what Spirit they are of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of them ſeem to trace back the Practices of thoſe Times, in which it was neither ſufficient, nor ſafe, for a man to declare for the King, but he muſt be for the King and Parliament too: till at laſt, he muſt upon his peril, diſclaim both King and Parliament. Whereas in reality, Loyalty to the King, and Juſtice to the People, are in their very Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſo united together, that they are incapable of ſeparation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort ſeem to have forgotten, or even deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſo-much boaſted Principle of <hi>their own Church,</hi> which they uſe to ſay, is not of a Perſecuting <hi>Genius</hi> or Spirit; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, peradventure they mean by a Diſtinction, that it is ſo in its <hi>Articles,</hi> but not in its <hi>Members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that we may ſpare both theſe ſorts of Spirits, and calm them too, I will ſay no more of either, but only this, That I am ſent hither to ſerve a Prince, who makes it His buſineſs to content both; who to all His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, however affected, is a Mirrour of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> And as I cannot <hi>ſerve,</hi> ſo neither can I <hi>pleaſe</hi> Him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then by uſing my beſt endeavours (as by God's Grace I ever ſhall in what-ever comes before me) that the effects of theſe two God-like Attributes in Him, may be equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to all, without regard to Fear or Favour.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I told you in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, that the cauſe of all theſe Jealouſies and Diſaffections, was that great diſtraction in Opinion and Judgment, wherewith this Age has been divided and perplex'd, while each one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to maintain and promote his own; ſometimes one prevailing, and ſometimes another, and all equally labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if not for Power, at leaſt for Eaſe and Security. Give me leave to entertain you a little with the cauſe of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions in Opinions, which are the cauſe of theſe Diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. I hope the Remarks which I ſhall make, will prove no miſ-expence of time, either to you or me.</p>
            <p>This great and famous Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> being many Ages paſt, (as again now at preſent) highly bleſt with Kings, enrich'd with a moſt ſublime Wiſdom, as well as other Princely Vertues: The Government of it was many hundred years ſince, founded on ſuch Rocks of Prudence and Juſtice,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105927:4"/>as might in all humane proſpect have ſecured it unſhaken to the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>It is that of Monarchy, which has for its pattern the Great Monarch of Heaven, and of all created Beings. A Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy by Deſcent, which ſecures us from all thoſe diſmal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Wars, which commonly attends the Election of Kings, to the great weakning, and oft-times final deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Government and People. A Monarchy, wherein the King has all the Power, the Nobility all the Honour, and the People all the Security, which the Hearts of men truly Rational, can wiſh or aſpire to.</p>
            <p>How often, and with what great Solemnity, hath the great Charter of the Subjects Liberty and Property received Confirmation from the glorious Anceſtors of our preſent Reigning Monarch? What Spot of Ground is there thrô the whole circumference of the Earth, where the Subject lives ſo free, ſo plentiful, and ſo ſecure from any ſort of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as in this our truly fortunate Iſland? What man ſo low, as (not offending the Laws) to need fear his moſt potent Neighbour? Again, What Nobleman ſo Great as to dare either by force or treachery, to attempt either upon the Royal Authority or Publick Peace? Laſtly, What Throne ſo fix'd and unmoveable as Ours? Since the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prerogatives are ſo inalienable from the Crown, that even the moſt ſolemn Acts of our Kings (when found inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with their perſonal ſafety and Government, and the good and ſafety of their Subjects) are of no manner of force, to reſtrain the exerciſe of their Regal Power? This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the King's Declaration in the 15th of <hi>Edward</hi> 3d, Printed with the Statutes, and by many other inſtances which might be produced.</p>
            <p>After ſuch Foundations laid, after ſuch regular and well-poliſh'd Architecture in the whole Frame of this our happy Government; when, moreover, our Kings have at their Call the moſt Auguſt Senate in the World, whoſe Duty it is to ſtrengthen the Hands of the Soveraign, by their Counſels, and the Kingdom's Treaſure, as Emergencies ariſe. How comes it to paſs, that we have ſeen and felt effects not only far ſhort, but even contrary to ſuch glorious Cauſes? to paſs by our ceaſing now for a long time to advance our Nations
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105927:4"/>Glory, by Acquiſitions abroad, (tho' we have not wanted Princes of great Abilities and Inclinations that way). How comes it to paſs, that we have with much difficulty conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our own from Forreign Encroachments. Nay, laſtly, how has it come to paſs, that we have ſuffered ſuch fatal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions at home, among our ſelves, by which the whole Frame of our Government hath been ſhaken in pieces, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſeen but Horrour and Confuſion, nothing to be expected, but utter Ruine and Deſtruction?</p>
            <p>To anſwer theſe important Queries, thô private Malice Pride, Luſt and Avarice be the immediate incentives of all who are Authors or Fomenters of all Civil Diſſenſion; yet manifeſt it is, that this ſo great decay from the Ancient vigour of our Government, and the many Difficulties in which it is of late ſo deeply involved, have ariſen principally, if not purely, from the Cauſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>'Twas a memorable ſaying that of my late Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour <hi>Clarendon,</hi> to the two Houſes of Parliament, ſoon after his late Majeſty's happy Reſtauration: <hi>It is,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubject, and that which has cost the King many a Sigh, many a ſad Hour, to conſider, that that very thing, which was appointed by God as a Cement of Affection, betwixt Strangers and Enemies,</hi> Religion, <hi>ſhould now become the fiercest Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Strife between the dearest Friends and nearest Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Conſideration carries me back to examine, from what time, and from what cauſe, this unhappy effect of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had its firſt riſe: For were it indeed to be found in the Root or Eſſence of Chriſtianity it ſelf, I ſhould conceive the Reception of ſuch a Religion into the World, and its ſo long continuance amidſt ſo many Nations, to be a greater Miracle, than any that was ever wrought for its Birth or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation. But I take the fact to be far otherwiſe:</p>
            <p>For upon the firſt Planting of Chriſtianity, the Apoſtles (inſpired with the Holy Ghoſt) all taught one and the ſame Truths; which their Diſciples held themſelves obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and for ever keep inviolate and intire, as proceeding all from one and the ſame eternal Verity: and when afterwards any difference aroſe concerning what was ſo taught, or what not: The general practice of Chriſtians was, to ſubmit to the determination of their Paſtors, either Single, or in a Provincial, National or General Council, as the exigency of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105927:5"/>the matter required, and the circumſtances of the time and place allowed. Which left no room for pertinacy in Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at leaſt, not any poſſibility of diſturbing the publique Peace.</p>
            <p>And by this means Chriſtianity remained in this Kingdom unſhaken, from its firſt entry, until about the 24th year of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, when that unhappy Prince, not finding from his long and chargeable Addreſſes to <hi>Rome,</hi> a paſſage to the Enjoyment of a ſecond Wife (the firſt then living) breaks that Power he was not able to bend, and levels whatever oppoſes to his unbridled Appetite: and maugre <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> (which in <hi>the first place</hi> grants, that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be free, and all her Rights and Liberties inviolable,) the Treaſures and Revenues of the Church, nay, its very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and Lands are no longer ſpared, than that King's Profuſions needed not freſh Supplies.</p>
            <p>To this end, by an Act in the 26 of his Reign, the King is declared Head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in Spirituals, and that under the Penalty of High Treaſon to deny it. But this Sounding Monſtrous Novel, many of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Learning and Piety, who could not believe what they had never before heard, nor pretend to believe, what really they did not, loſt their Lives and Fortunes, and that with all the outward marks of Infamy.</p>
            <p>The Fence being thus broken down, whereby Unity had been thus long preſerved, no wonder if way was ſoon made for multiplying of Opinions: For People being once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, they had been taught one untruth, and that in a point of ſo great importance, as the Headſhip of the Church in Spirituals; how could they forbear to doubt, whether they were not impoſed upon, and taught Untruths in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, ſince both the one and the other depended on the ſame Authority? And to what other Oracle could they then poſſibly reſort for the ſolution of their Doubts, but either to the mere Letter of the Scriptures, on all hands admitted to be God's Word, or elſe every man to his own Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for himſelf? Since, if the Church it ſelf had been ſo foully deceived therein, and therefore forſaken by them, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly no other could pretend Authority to deliver the true Sence, ſo as to oblige others to the belief of it.</p>
            <p>But the King himſelf having lookt upon that Power as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105927:5"/>which had been ever before Superiour to him in Spirituals, could now leſs brook any control or contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from His own Subjects, over whoſe Souls and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces He aſſumed a more abſolute Dominion, than ever any Pope had done before, or any King of <hi>England</hi> over their Bodies or Eſtates.</p>
            <p>By this abſolute Spiritual Power, he thought to put a ſtop to that great difference of Opinions which multiplied every day: and backing the ſaid Spiritual Power with Authority of Parliaments, which he had always at his beck, and ready for his turn, he began <hi>first</hi> to think of ſome means of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Diſſenters</hi> by <hi>Acts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> and then to make <hi>Teſts,</hi> much like to our Modern ones, as to the meekneſs of their Stile, thô a little point-blank as to their matter: For in the 31ſt of his Reign, it is Enacted, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any hold, that in the Sacrament of the Altar, there is not preſent the Natural Body and Bloud of our Saviour, born of the Bleſſed Virgin; or that any ſubſtance of Bread and Wine ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains after Conſecration, he ſhall be Burnt, and otherwiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, as in caſe of High Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any hold Communion under both Kinds neceſſary, or that Prieſts or Religious may Marry, or oppoſe private Maſſes, or deny Auricular Confeſſion; or if a Priest or Religious Perſon Marry, they ſhall ſuffer Death, and forfeit as in the caſe of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by theſe <hi>Antiproteſtant-Teſts,</hi> very many (well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons no doubt) were violently hurried out of their Lives and Fortunes, with as much (I would ſay with as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) Reaſon and Juſtice, as they have been of late: For ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide on which part the Truth of thoſe points did lie; men being left to their own private Interpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, exempted from all Authority of the Church, how could they ever bring themſelves to believe what they could not find in their own Senſe of Scripture-Words? or why ſhould they be forced to become Hypocrites, and pretend to believe what they did not?</p>
            <p>Again, by a Statute of 32 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. it was Enacted, that all Decrees and Ordinances which (according to God's Word) ſhould be ordained in matters of Faith and Religion, by the Biſhops and others thereto appointed by the King's Letters Pattents, ſhould be obeyed and believed by all the King's Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105927:6"/>
            <p>The King, in whom then reſted the final reſult of all Controverſies in Religion, would no doubt ever Judge all his own Decrees to be according to God's Word. So here was an Implicite Faith to be yeilded not onely to what the King <hi>then</hi> had, but to whatever more he ſhould <hi>hereafter</hi> decree. A Burden ſure too heavy for any man, that had any ſence of any Religion at all.</p>
            <p>In the 24 and 25 of the ſame King, it was Enacted, <hi>That all Engliſh Bibles of</hi> Tyndal<hi>'s Tranſlation, and other Engliſh Books of Faith, Religion or Scripture, contrary to the Doctrine ſet forth, ſince</hi> 1540. <hi>or to be ſet forth by the King, ſhould be Aboliſhed. None ſhould deride or deſpiſe ſuch Doctrine: none ſhall retain Books for Maintenance of Anabaptiſm, or other Books ſupprest, or to be ſupprest by the King's Proclamation. The Bible ſhall not be read in Engliſh by the common People. Nothing ſhall be taught contrary to the King's Injunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Statute of the 37 of the ſame King, it is declared, That <hi>the King hath full Authority to Correct all Hereſies and Errours, and to exerciſe all other manner of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and that the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Perſons, have no manner of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</hi> [And if ſo, then they derive no more from Chriſt, than what is common to the meaneſt Mechanick.]</p>
            <p>By a Statute of the 35 of the ſame King, Power is given him to name ſixteen Spiritual and ſixteen Temporal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom he pleaſed, to eſtabliſh all ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Laws, as he and they thought fit.</p>
            <p>So Volatile and Floating was Religion in thoſe days; and yet every change, under great Penalties to be obeyed.</p>
            <p>And thus did this poor unfortunate Prince weary out himſelf in difficulties moſt inſuperable, to conſtrain by cruel Laws the Belief of his own tottering Doctrines, after he had driven his Subjects from all reliance on thoſe Eſtabliſhed by the Church.</p>
            <p>But ſuch doings againſt Nature and Reaſon, can have no longer duration, than either Violence does compel, or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt bribe Obedience: and therefore, notwithſtanding all thoſe coſtly Baits of Church-Lands, with which he had drawn the Nobility and Commons to a Compliance; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe many hideous Executions, with which he had terrified <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> during his life; laſtly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105927:6"/>the careful choice and rigorous charge given to thoſe to whoſe Government he committed, by Teſtament, the Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Succeſſour; he is no ſooner laid in his Grave, but all he had done is overthrown and buried with him: All, I ſay, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>the Supremacy,</hi> that is, the Source and Fountain of all the Miſeries which had already befallen the one Party, and a Power of making as much Havock upon the Souls, Bodies, and Fortunes of the other, when time ſhould ſerve.</p>
            <p>And accordingly by an Act of the 2 and 3 of <hi>Edward</hi> 6th, [reciting, That <hi>the King</hi> (who was then a Child) <hi>had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed certain Biſhops and Learned Men to make an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Order of Common-Prayer and Sacraments, which,</hi> ſays the Statute, <hi>by the aid of the Holy Ghost, they had done:</hi> Thô very incoherent with any thing done by <hi>Henry</hi> 8. who no leſs pretended to the aid of the ſame Holy Ghoſt] you have a new <hi>Anticatholie Test</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, That <hi>if any refuſe, or uſe any other, or ſpeak contemptibly of this,</hi> (the Makers, it ſeems, were very apprehenſive of being laught at for their pains) <hi>they ſhould ſuffer the Deprivations, Forfeitures, and Impriſonments in that Act appointed.</hi> And this was further inforced by a Statute of the 5 and 6 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. which obliges all to come to Church on all Sundays and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidays.</p>
            <p>And by an Act of the 3 and 4 of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Cap. 11. <hi>The King had power to name thirty two perſons, to compile ſuch Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws, as he and they thought fit:</hi> And Cap. 12. <hi>To name twelve to ſettle the Form of Making and Conſecrating Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The inferences from all theſe Acts, are ſo natural, obvious and eaſie, that I ſhall leave every man to his own Remarks on them.</p>
            <p>But this again held not long; for by an Act of the 1ſt of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> all that was done before, concerning Religion, was again Repealed: and the Sanguinary Severities of this Queen's Reign were no leſs ineffectual and deplorable, than thoſe of her Father and Brother. They were indeed deſign'd to reſtore that Spiritual Church Authority, which, when ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, can alone prevent or heal all Diſſenſions about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: but they had a quite contrary effect, and left thoſe whom they pretended to reduce, in a far greater degree of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and averſion from all Peace and Reconciliation, than they were before.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105927:7"/>
            <p>To her ſucceeded Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the Throne, as ſhe did her Brother in the Supremacy: For, as he, a Child, ſo now ſhe, a Woman, (forbidden by God's Laws, ſo much as to ſpeak in the Church) aſcends the Chair, and declares her ſelf <hi>Supreme Governour</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And by an Act of the 1ſt of her Reign, <hi>Power is given to her and her Succeſſors, to Reform, Correct, and Amend all Errours, Hereſies, Schiſms, and Offences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this time, ſuch an Inundation of Penal and Sanguina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Laws, to compel the Worſhip of this Idol ſo ſet up, as would require more than this whole day to enumerate.</p>
            <p>But I am the more willing to inſtance in ſome of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſhe that began to employ her Two-edged Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, againſt all ſorts of Diſſenters, as well Proteſtant as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick: and from her too exemplary zeal for Uniformity, have ſprung all thoſe Penal Laws, by which either her ſelf or Succeſſors, have endeavour'd to maintain the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by depreſſing all others.</p>
            <p>Twelve Pence a <hi>Sunday</hi> is a mere Trifle in the eye of a thoughtleſs rich man, who perhaps is in no danger of paying it: But how ſupportable to a poor Labourer, perhaps lame too, or blind, old, or ſick, and with a Family to maintain? and at laſt, for his <hi>diſſent</hi> alone, excluded from the relief even of a morſel of Bread from the Pariſh.</p>
            <p>The Twenty Pound a Month is no great matter from men of large Eſtates: But how impoſſible to be paid by him that has leſs? and yet Body, Lands, and Goods, muſt all go to make it out.</p>
            <p>The two Thirds of a <hi>Diſſenter's</hi> Lands, muſt indeed needs pinch cloſe even upon the greateſt; for men of Eſtates are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated to ſuitable Expences, and are generally under as great difficulties, to keep within their bounds, as thoſe of ſmaller For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: How then can they ſubſiſt after two Thirds are lopt off?</p>
            <p>But all this, thô tending to the ruine and famiſhing, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Offender, but of his innocent Wife, Children and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; yet you may ſay, it breaks no bones, nor extends to life: <hi>But the end is not yet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man doubts but that a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholic is a Chriſtian, and alſo a Member of the True Church; (thô he as alſo every one is) Erroneous in the opinion of every man that differs from him: Yet by a Statute of 13 <hi>Eliz. If any man ſhall reconcile
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105927:7"/>another, or be reconciled himſelf to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>both Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler and Reconciled, ſhall be puniſhed as Traytors; and that without any regard, whether the perſon Reconciled were before</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, Turk, Jew, <hi>or</hi> Atheiſt.</p>
            <p>No Man denies, that a Prieſt of the Roman Church is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ordained, for the Exerciſe of Spiritual Functions: <hi>Yet if any ſuch, being a Subject of this Kingdom, do but ſet his foot on Engliſh Ground, his Native Country, without other Offence, he ſhall ſuffer as a Traytor,</hi> 27 Eliz. chap. 2.</p>
            <p>It is known, that the Exerciſe of the Roman Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion cannot be without the help of Prieſts, yet <hi>if any Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or but Relieve any ſuch, he ſhall be puniſht with Death, as a Felon,</hi> 27 Eliz. chap. 2.</p>
            <p>Many about us have felt the ſmart of the Laws againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles. But by the Statute of 35 of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> we find, that <hi>if any abſenting from Church, a Month, ſhall afterward reſort to a Conventicle, he ſhall be committed to Priſon; and, if he Conform not within three Months, he ſhall abjure the Realm, or ſuffer as a Felon, without Benefit of Clergy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, one would think, were ſomewhat ſevere, and that any tolerable degree of Truth thus guarded, might be of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient force to reſiſt the Batteries of all Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>And yet in ſo dreadful a manner has this unhappy Land been ever ſince haunted with Panick and Imaginary Fears, that notwithſtanding all this, and whatever more the Wit and Art of Man have been able to do or invent, for the ſecuring of their Church, they have been always calling for more, as oft as there is a Seſſions of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Out of which Fear have at laſt ſprung up their Two Darl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acts; The firſt of the 25th of the late King, Entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent the Danger ariſing from Popiſh Recuſants.</hi> And thereby, <hi>All that ſhall not take the Sacraments, Swear, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, (as is therein required) are Excluded His Majeſty's Service.</hi> The other in the 30th of the late King, Entituled, <hi>An Act for the more effectual Preſervation of the King's Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And this Excludes from Parliament <hi>All,</hi> and from the King's preſence, <hi>Many,</hi> that ſhall not <hi>Swear and Declare, as is therein required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe are Acts of Parliament, they ought to be Treated with Reſpect, and Underſtood in ſuch a Sence as may Conſiſt with Loyalty, and the Being of Government; that is, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105927:8"/>That Great and Wiſe Body had no other intent, then what the Title and Preamble of thoſe Acts ſeem to import, <hi>viz.</hi> The King's Security from the Danger of Admitting into his Service, Council, or Preſence, by Surprize, or Inadvertency, ſuch as they then conceived not likely to be faithful to him. Yet not mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thruſt from him, any of whoſe Truth and Abilities he himſelf ſhould be aſſured, and as occaſion required, ſhould call, and by his Royal Diſpenſation enable to ſerve him.</p>
            <p>But in the Sence, to which Theſe Acts have been ſince Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, I may ſay Andaciouſly Wreſted, that is, ſo to Tye up the King's hands, that he ſhall by no Means, nor on any Extremity be capable of receiving Aid, Succour, and Service from ſo many Thouſands of his Subjects, (how Faithful or Able ſoever) as ſhall believe it either not lawful to Swear at all, or not to <hi>Do, Swear</hi> and <hi>Declare,</hi> as is required; or, whatever their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be, ſhall neglect to do it, when required: This were to raiſe up the Acts into a Mortal War againſt themſelves, and to pervert <hi>The more effectual Means of the King's Preſervation and Government,</hi> Pretended, into a more Real and Certain Ruin and Deſtruction of Both, Intended: And ſurely, it were but a ſorry Compliment to ſo many Great Men, as were concern'd in the Paſſing of theſe Acts, to tell them at this time, that this was indeed their very Meaning.</p>
            <p>We all know, Gentlemen, that by the Act of the 25th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>To Compaſs or Imagin the Death of the King is High Treaſon.</hi> But this Compaſſing is not reſtrained to the narrow Compaſs of Deſigning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſent Execution, by Poyſon, Dagger, Screwed Guns, and Chewed Silver Bullets only. No, our Laws interpret this Compaſſing to a far more extended ſence.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> (tho' then no friend to the Prerogative) tells us, that he that declares by Overt act, to Depoſe the King, does enough to prove, he Compaſſes the King's Death. And ſo it is, to Impriſon, or Take the King into his Power. For there is but a ſmall diſtance between Depoſing or Impriſoning the King, and his Death. So that whoſoever Compaſſeth the one, virtually and obliquely, thô not directly, Compaſſes the other alſo.</p>
            <p>In the Caſe of the R. Reverend Father, Dr. <hi>Plunket,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who fell one of the Victims to the late celebrated Plot: An Intention to raiſe Rebellion, was by my late Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Pemberton</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Treaſon, becauſe Rebellion does include an Intention of the King's Death.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105927:8"/>
            <p>So, in the late Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe, an Intention of Seizing the King's Guards was adjudged Treaſon, becauſe Depriving the King of his Defence, does imply a Compaſſing of his Death.</p>
            <p>So to detain the King's Fortreſſes or Ships of War, is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the King's Death, becauſe ſo conſiderable a part of that ſtrength, which is to defend his Life, is withheld from him.</p>
            <p>And I my ſelf have heard our preſent King, moſt admirably and rightly obſerve, that that Monſtrous Treaſon and Rebellion here in <hi>England</hi> againſt his late Glorious Father, began not in 42, as is vulgarly ſuppoſed, but long before, by the Trains and Lines prepared for it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are a few of the many Inſtances I could give on this Subject. I pray you, then, what Interpretation can be made of ſuch Endeavors for Excluding and Wreſting from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Service and Preſence, and from his Counſel in Parliament, ſo vaſt a Number of his Subjects, (more valuable than Forts or Ships) of whoſe Fidelity and Capacity to ſerve him, he has the utmoſt aſſurance. Looks not this ſomewhat like taking him into their Power, who thus Thruſt others from him? And who knows, but in time to come, the Number thus exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, may be ten times greater than now it is? And who knows alſo, but many of thoſe, who make no ſcruple of the Teſts, may yet pretend it, or whether they pretend it or no, may yet forbear them, of ſet purpoſe, to defert his Service; till between ſuch as cannot, and ſuch as will not take them, under pretence of Conformity to Law, we ſhall have at laſt, a King left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one Subject, to Counſel, Obey, or Come near him.</p>
            <p>Under this Contemplation, of what now really is, and what hereafter may farther happen, with what face can any but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Loyalty, and not to be open Enemies to their King, their Country, and the Publick Peace, when at the ſame time, they cling and hug themſelves up in ſo Pernicious or perhaps Treaſonous Interpretation of theſe Two Acts. And what Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Indignation againſt them, muſt it needs create in every man, that has but the leaſt ſpark of Loyalty left in his breaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> My buſineſs is not here to declare what I take to be true or falſe in Matters of Religion, nor to advance the one, nor depreſs the other. What I ſpeak of, is only in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Publick Peace, which, as much as in me lies, is my Duty to promote.</p>
            <p>To this end it is, that I have given you here, for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105927:9"/>a very ſhort (tho' for our time too large a) Scheme of many of the great Mutations in Religion here in <hi>England,</hi> of late times, by Publick Authority, and of ſome few of the many ſharp Laws, from time to time invented, by each prevailing Party, to force the ſubmiſſion of others.</p>
            <p>The multitude of Men and even of whole Families, not only that have ſuffer'd, but have been driven into Foreign Lands, or ruin'd and ſwallow'd up by thoſe Devouring Laws, are even beyond account or any Man's power to number up. Where, by the way, it muſt be obſerved, that the very ſuffering is a clear proof of the ſincerity and well-meaning, tho' it cannot be always of the truth of the ſufferer.</p>
            <p>And after all this Havock, where every little Knave receives encouragement, to inſult over and make a prey of his more worthy Neighbour, at length up comes this Brace of <hi>Teſts,</hi> Midwiv'd into Acts, by the aid of perſons, then fam'd indeed for Patriots, but ſoon after Notorious in the enſuing Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſucceeded as their Natural Iſſue, by a Plot that is the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of our Nation, or rather, The Plot and later Teſts, Twin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children of the firſt, ſucceeded alſo by Votes for Excluding his preſent Majeſty from his Inheritance, by an Horrible Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, againſt the Lives of our preſent and late King; and by the Great and Dangerous Rebellion of <hi>England;</hi> and now at laſt, to the World's wonder, and their own ſhame, moſt cloſely, and that in the worſt ſence, adhered unto, by ſuch Vain Boaſters of Loyalty, as would allow no ſhare of it to any part of the World but themſelves; thô by this very adherence their own ſhare of it becomes far too little for any prudent Prince to rely on.</p>
            <p>But at length, God Almighty in his Mercy hath given us a King, whoſe Heart he has inſpired with Wiſdom, to diſcern the Imprudence as well as Injuſtice of all theſe Severe Laws, with mildneſs to admit a general Abolition of them all; tho' from many of them great Riches have been, and might ſtill be, drawn to the Crown, and with Fortitude to proſecute with an undaunted Courage, as well as indefatigable Labour, ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Work, tho' ſtrongly encountred therein, by Two ſorts of men; Both, I confeſs, too numerous, and in their own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions very mighty, and as many more, as either of theſe are able to impoſe upon, or deceive.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105927:9"/>
            <p>The one, ſuch as being unacquainted with the uſe of Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or not liking the labour of it, imagine, Religion can be no longer kept up, than it is, Gig-like, laſht into motion; and yet themſelves much too tender to bear the leaſt touch. And yet again, thrô want of Thought, expoſe themſelves to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt peril, not foreſeeing, that they cannot be ſure to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uppermoſt; and when not ſo, the Penalties they prepare or retain for others, fall directly on their own heads.</p>
            <p>The other ſort, ſuch whoſe manner of life ſeems to indicate little other ſenſe of Religion, than a fear leſt their vicious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms ſhould fall under ſome reſtraint by the Practice of it.</p>
            <p>Right Religion conſiſts not in Violence, Noiſe or Tumult: God was not in the Whirl-wind, nor in the Earthquake, nor in the Fire, when he ſpoke to <hi>Elias,</hi> but in the ſtill ſmall Voice. Religion rather conſiſts in Meekneſs, long Suffering, and doing as we would have others do to us.</p>
            <p>We have our Saviour's word, <hi>That a Kingdom divided can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand.</hi> Now, there are but two ways imaginable, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſuch a Diviſion among Chriſtians, can poſſibly be avoided, as muſt elſe neceſſarily terminate in the utter overthrow of Chriſtianity it ſelf; which is Chriſt's own Kingdom, and which every Chriſtian muſt needs abhor to think of.</p>
            <p>One is by the general Submiſſion of particular Chriſtians to one common Authority; which, how much ſoever to be wiſht for, cannot now be ſuppoſed practicable; and therefore no more need be ſaid of that. The other is, by bearing with one anothers differences in Religion, and in letting every man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his own, without offending, or being offended at his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>This later His Majeſty has graciouſly choſen: He has not only already granted a general Indulgence, (which yet can laſt but during Pleaſure) but he is alſo ready totally to diſſolve our Bonds, and ſet us ſo free, that even his own or Succeſſor's hands ſhall not be able to hurt us, for matters of Religion: And this by a <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> as ſolemn and ſacred, as that by which we enjoy our Lives and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>What then remains on our parts? Muſt we always imitate the hardned <hi>Jews</hi> in murmuring againſt our moſt Benign Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, againſt God himſelf, and nauſeate the Quails and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na he ſends us? Muſt we always (Slave-like) hug the Chains which tye up both King and People, not onely from reſtoring
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105927:10"/>the Kingdom's Glory abroad, but even from its neceſſary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at home? Or ought we not rather, with united Hearts, firſt offer up our Thanks and Praiſes to God, in whoſe Hands are the Hearts of Kings, for having put it into the King's heart to do ſuch good things for his People: Next, to preſent our unanimous Thanks, in an Humble Addreſs, to His Majeſty; and then, with as united hands, and with all the power we have, to ſerve and aſſiſt Him: Which, at this time, we can no ways bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do, than by employing our utmoſt endeavours to Find and Elect for Parliament, when called, ſuch Members, as we may be ſure, or reaſonably hope, will readily and chearfully joyn with His Majeſty in this ſo Pious, Prudent, Charitable, and kind Determination, joyned with our hearty Prayers for the good ſucceſs of it.</p>
            <p>It remains now, Gentlemen of the Jury, that I Addreſs my ſelf particularly to you, and that I give you in charge, what Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences you are to make enquiry of for this preſent Seſſions: But I am ſenſible that I have already treſpaſſed ſufficiently upon the Patience of the Court; and thô the importance of my Subject be really ſo great and conſiderable, both for the Service of His Majeſty, and for the Welfare of us all, that it does very well ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the length of my Diſcourſe, yet that I may not render it tedious without neceſſity, I ſhall wave at preſent all enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch particular matters, as make the uſual and ordinary ſubject of a Charge: You your ſelves, Gentlemen, are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted of what nature they are: and Indictments and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments will be brought in to you, for all ſuch more urgent matters, as ſhall need and require a more ſpecial Conſideration and Redreſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 4. l. 19. read <hi>need to fear.</hi> p. 8. l. 21. after Juriſdiction, 1. <hi>but by from and under His Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
